Guide to the Waldo Huntley Heinrichs Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Waldo Huntley Heinrichs Papers
1901-1959
RG 115
Yale University Divinity School Library
5
(9 boxes and 2 oversize containers)
Correspondence, writings, diaries, and photographs document Heinrichs career with the YMCA and his service with the U.S. Air Force. Letters and diaries of Waldo Heinrichs' sister Margaret shed additional light on the period of time that the Heinrichs spent in India 1930-1931. Waldo Heinrichs served as a YMCA secretary in Hawaii, India, and Jerusalem. from 1913 to 1934. He then became Professor of Contemporary Civilization at Middlebury College. He was a pilot for the U.S. Air Force during World War I, and a Combat Intelligence Officer during World War II.
Heinrichs, Waldo Huntley, 1891-1959
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Heinrichs family.
Biographical / Historical
1891 Born in British India, son of Jacob and Lydia Heinrichs, American Baptist educational missionaries
1913 B.A., Denison University, Ohio; later received M.A. in European History from Columbia University, New York
1913-1915 Fellowship Secretary, Y.M.C.A., Honolulu
1915-1916 First American Y.M.C.A. Secretary to work with British troops in India
1917-1919 First aviation cadet in Army Ground School at M.I.T. Distinguished service with U.S. Army Air Force in Europe. Shot down, severely wounded in September, 1918 and held prisoner until Armistice. Decorated with Croix de Guerre with Palm and other awards.
1919-1924 Head of Lecture Department, National Council of Y.M.C.A.'s of India, Burma, and Ceylon
1926-1930 Associate General Secretary, Y.M.C.A., Lahore, India
1930-1931 Waldo's sister Margaret stayed with the family in India
1931-1934 General Secretary, Y.M.C.A., Jerusalem
1935-1942 Professor of Contemporary Civilization, Middlebury College, Middlebury, Vermont
1942-1944 Combat Intelligence Officer in 66th Fighter Wing, VIII Fighter Command of 8th Air Force in England
195-1956 Professor of Contemporary Civilization, Middlebury College
1959 Died
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence
II. Writings and Notes
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia
IV. Photographs
V. Diaries
VI. Letters and Diaries of Margaret Heinrichs
These papers are of interest for their documentation of Heinrichs' work with the YMCA in India and Jerusalem. Complementary papers are located in the YMCA archives at the University of Minnesota. The collection includes twenty-six diary volumes dating from 1909 to 1945, photographs, clippings, and letters, including some related to Heinrichs' YMCA service. He resigned from the YMCA in 1934 following a disagreement with the International Committee concerning Nazi anti-Semitic newspapers in the reading room of the Jerusalem YMCA Heinrichs was a friend of John R. Mott and Sherwood Eddy and twice participated in the Sherwood Eddy Travel Seminar in Europe. These papers are also of interest because Heinrichs was a child of missionaries and spent a good part of his youth separated form his parents. A few letters written later in life to his children explore the implications of his early experience.
The Letters and Diaries of Margaret Heinrichs in Series VI shed additional light on the activities of the Heinrichs family in India during 1930-1931.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings and Notes
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia
IV. Photographs
V. Diaries
VI. Letters and Diaries of Margaret Heinrichs
Young Men's Christian Associations -- India; Young Men's Christian Associations -- Jerusalem; Heinrichs, Waldo Huntley, 1891-1959
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Family correspondence
    - Letters to/from family, including regarding the death of Heinrichs' brother Edgar in 1910, a letter to his wife regarding the Jerusalem YMCA situation in 1934, and letters written from Europe in 1939, which describe the prelude to World War II., 1906-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1-19)
  - General correspondence
    - General correspondence, 1910-1913 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Letter from Lord Allenby, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Regarding Land-lease bill, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Regarding WWII service of WHH, 1941-1944, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Letters from YMCA friends, 1945-1953 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - General correspondence, No date (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Addendum to correspondence
    - Waldo Huntley Heinrichs correspondence
      - Letters to family enroute to and in France, 1917 Jul -Sep (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Letters to family while in France with American Expeditionary Force, 1917 Oct-1918 Dec (Box 9, Folder 2-6)
      - Letters to family while in New York, 1919 January-October (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Letter to wife, Dorothy from France, 1917 Nov (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Letters to Dorothy from NYC and London, 1934 Sep, 1939 Jun (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Letters to Dorothy from England while with 66th Fighter Wing, 1943 May - 1944 August (Box 9, Folder 10-13)
      - Letters to Dorothy: fragments, No date (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence of others
      - Adjutant General Office - re. prisoners of war, 1918 Nov (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - WHH's mother, 1917 Jun (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - Memorandum - Report by Harmon on settlement of newspaper controversy in Jerusalem YMCA, 1934 Sep (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Writings and Notes, Series II
  - "Our Heritage of Freedom" - history of the VIII Fighter Command of the 8th U.S. Army Air Force, No date (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Diary excerpt, 1939 August (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Lecture notes regarding WWI, No date (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Lecture notes re. world situation, foreign policy, No date (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
  - Lecture notes of Heinrichs' father Jacob on religions of India, No date (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series III
  - Genealogical and family records: documents, 1908-1949, no date (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Genealogical and family records: correspondence, 1925-1950 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Genealogical and family records: notes, No date (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Biographical documentation: Elementary school, 1901-1905 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Biographical documentation: High school, 1906-1909 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Biographical documentation: re. death of Edgar Heinrichs, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Biographical documentation: College, 1910-1913 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Yearbook of Denison University 1913 (Box Ov2)
  - Biographical documentation: YMCA work, Hawaii, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Biographical documentation: World War I service, 1918-1921 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Biographical documentation: YMCA work - India, Jerusalem, 1931-1934 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Biographical documentation: World War II service, 1942-1944 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Biographical documentation: Denison honorary doctorate, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Biographical documentation: Death, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Biographical documentation: Miscellaneous, 1959-1962 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Notebook relating to Waldo Heinrichs Scholarship at Middlebury College, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Guest book; anniversaries book; address book; Hindu Heaven by Max Wylie, friend of Heinrichs in India; 2 letters from ancestors of Dorothy Heinrichs, 1862-1936 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Scrapbook of memorabilia and clippings; Croix de Guerre citation; grammar school and high school diplomas (Box Ov1)
- Photographs, Series IV
  - Loose photographs (Box 4, Folder 54-55)
  - Photo album of YMCA scout camp in India, No date (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Photo album of scenes in India, No date (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Loose negatives, includes India, 1906-1913 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Albums of negatives, No date (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Family photo album (Box Ov2)
- Diaries, Series V
  Scope and Contents
  There are a total of 26 diary volumes, with fairly regular and detailed daily entries. They are of interest for their documentation of Heinrichs' personal life as well as his work overseas.
  - Diary volumes, 1909-1932 (Box 7, Folder 60-64)
  - Diary volumes, 1933-1945 (Box 8, Folder 65-69)
- Letters and Diaries of Margaret Heinrichs, Series VI
  - Correspondence
    - Letters written to parents while on world tour, 1930 Jun-Aug (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Letters to parents from India, 1930 Sep-1931 Feb (Box 9, Folder 19-21)
    - Letters to parents from India, Jerusalem, Egypt, 1931 Mar-Apr (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Diaries and Notes
    - Written while sailing Pacific, in Japan, in India, including notes about India and record of expenditures in India, 1930 Jun - Sep 2 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Written from Lahore and on trip back through Europe, 1930 Sep 3 - 1931 May 15 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Trip to Israel and other locations with parents, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Record of expenditures in Israel, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Tourist brochures, Jerusalem, Paris, ca. 1933 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Transcripts of letters and diaries
    Transcripts prepared by nephew.
    - Maps, introduction, contents, chapters 1-11, 1930 Jun-1931 May (Box 9, Folder 28-32)